<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Joseph M. Westenberg</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Joseph M. Westenberg</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Election Maps</title>
      <link>/teaching/electionmaps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/electionmaps/</guid>
      <description>After discovering the availability of some historical shapefiles from NHGIS and election data back to 2000 for many local elections from OpenElections, I wanted to assemble it for my personal research projects. While in the process of this I have started to map this data and make it available for readers to visualize patterns across time.
US Level Maps   For the following graphic the percentage of total vote the runner up received was subtracted from the percentage of vote that the victor received.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to Data Science</title>
      <link>/teaching/datasciencebook/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/datasciencebook/</guid>
      <description>An example of the code that is built through the workshops can be found on my GitHub.   More detailed notes as well as executed code can be found in my notes.    The goal of these short workshops is to give graduate students a very prelimenary introduction into coding in R. While having an instructor teach you these things may be helpful, in my belief, coding, like math, you have to learn by doing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping with Leaflet</title>
      <link>/blog/leaflet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/leaflet/</guid>
      <description>This post assumes a basic knowledge of R.
Using leaflet we can map shapefiles and specific points. As an illustrative example I will be using code I wrote earlier this year when I was looking into some questions regarding schools and state government. The shapefiles I will be using are the lower and upper legislatures for the state of Wisconsin. The points I will be mapping in the second post of this series will be specific school locations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Past Grill Photos</title>
      <link>/blog/pastgrill/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/blog/pastgrill/</guid>
      <description>Steak and Potatoes     Strip Steak seasoned with a balsamic vinegar rub and montreal steak seasoning. Fried potatoes and onions in a cast iron pan directly on the grill.
Veggie Assortment     This was my first time grilling veggies like this and they turned out stellar! A bit of olive oil, salt and pepper before tossing on the grill. Then made a balsamic vinegar drizzle for them: olive oil, balsamic vinegar, fresh rosemary, parsley, and sage.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Introduction to International Economics</title>
      <link>/teaching/interecon/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/teaching/interecon/</guid>
      <description>Instructor: Joseph Westenberg (jwesten@iu.edu)
Office Hours: T 1:00 - 3:00 PM (or by appointment) in Wylie Hall 244
Class: T &amp;amp; Th 4:00 - 5:15 PM in Ballantine Hall 342
Prerequisites: Intro to Microeconomics (E201) OR Intro to Microeconomics: Honors (S201)
Text: James Gerber&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;International Economics&amp;rdquo;, Seventh Edition
Course Description     This course provides a moderately in-depth look at some of the major topics in international economics that are quintessential for the economics major.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact</title>
      <link>/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Feb 2019 13:38:41 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/contact/</guid>
      <description>** Contact page don&amp;rsquo;t contain a body, just the front matter above. See form.html in the layouts folder.
Formspree requires a (free) account and new form to be set up. The link is made on the final published url in the field: Restrict to Domain. It is possible to register up to 2 emails free and you can select which one you want the forms to go to within Formspree in the Settings tab.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Select Research</title>
      <link>/publications/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publications/</guid>
      <description>Job Market Paper     Section 301 and Politics: Analysis of Tariff Exclusions     with Nikita Lopatin and Beverly Mendoza (2021) SSRN Working Paper Series No. 3885900
On SSRN: 6th most downloaded paper in Import/Export Strategies; 8th most downloaded paper in Models of Political Processes: Rent-Seeking, Elections, Legislatures, &amp;amp; Voting Behavior; 8th most downloaded paper in Trade Policy (9/17/2021)
Abstract: Section 301 tariffs were imposed as a consequence of China&amp;rsquo;s discriminatory business practices against American firms.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
