<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Joseph M. Westenberg</title>
    <link>/</link>
      <atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Joseph M. Westenberg</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Joseph Westenberg 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/logo_huc1be9e4e3ae24305730dfe0ccc5f8623_97775_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>Joseph M. Westenberg</title>
      <link>/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>lesson0</title>
      <link>/courses/intror/lesson0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/courses/intror/lesson0/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;getting-started-in-r&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting Started in R&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I assume you have R installed and running. There are plenty of guides online on how to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s first define some arrays within R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These can be numeric based, in this case integer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r numCode R numberLines&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;A&amp;lt;-c(5,6,7)  # 1
B&amp;lt;-c(7,8,9)  # 2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s dig into what is going on a bit more. We are telling R to define a vector, this is the c( ) part, with elements 1,2,3 and give that vector a name A. The backwards arrow tells R what is the name and what is the element we are defining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can make character based vectors as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r numCode R numberLines&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;C&amp;lt;-c(&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;b&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;c&amp;quot;)  # 1
D&amp;lt;-c(&amp;quot;d&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;e&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;f&amp;quot;)  # 2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can then combine these vectors into a dataframe (this is relevant for when we start thinking about reading in/manipulating actual data). Since all of our vectors are length three, we can easily create a dataframe (think a matrix) where our column names will be the name of the vectors, and the rows will be the elements of the vectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r numCode R numberLines&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;first_dataframe&amp;lt;-data.frame(A,B,C,D)  # 1
print(first_dataframe)                # 2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##   A B C D
## 1 5 7 a d
## 2 6 8 b e
## 3 7 9 c f&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now first_dataframe is going to be of similar format as we will typically have when we read in data from excel files into R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r numCode R numberLines&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;print(first_dataframe[1,])  # 1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##   A B C D
## 1 5 7 a d&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>lesson1</title>
      <link>/courses/intror/lesson1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/courses/intror/lesson1/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;project-organization&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Project Organization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we get started, let’s set up a folder for our project and create subfolders to keep things organized. For this project I recommend the following subfolders, which are a good minimum for organizing any project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;raw_data: This is where we will put our `preprocessed’ data we will be getting from MIT Election Lab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scripts: Where we will save all of our R-scripts in this folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;processed_data: If we want to save some intermediate data steps between raw data and our output.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tables: Any tex tables we generate we will save to this folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;figures: Any figures we generate we will save to this folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tex: Where we can have our paper and/or presentations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can make more folders if you feel it keeps you organized. The main point I want to make here is it is well worth your time to think about how you want to organize your project. Oftentimes if we jump right in without a plan, things become a jumbled mess. (If you want to go further with your organization strategies, I recommend looking into waf, specifically check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://econ-project-templates.readthedocs.io/en/stable/index.html&#34;&gt;Templates for Reproducible Research Projects in Economics&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My project folder now looks like this:
&lt;strong&gt;Insert image of folder&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;getting-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by downloading &lt;a href=&#34;https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataset.xhtml?persistentId=doi:10.7910/DVN/PEJ5QU#&#34;&gt;Senate data from MIT Election Lab’s website&lt;/a&gt;. Let’s choose the csv format and save it in your raw_data folder. Next let’s download &lt;a href=&#34;https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataset.xhtml?persistentId=doi:10.7910/DVN/IG0UN2&#34;&gt;House of Representatives data from MIT Election Lab&lt;/a&gt; again in csv format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reading-in-the-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reading in the data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s open up a blank R script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Section 301 and Politics: Analysis of Tariff Exemptions</title>
      <link>/project/sect_301/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/project/sect_301/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;p&gt;Submitted on 12/23/2020.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Redistricting and Economic Outcomes</title>
      <link>/talk/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 08:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/talk/example/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Slides can be added in a few ways:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Create&lt;/strong&gt; slides using Academic&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/managing-content/#create-slides&#34;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slides&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; feature and link using &lt;code&gt;slides&lt;/code&gt; parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Upload&lt;/strong&gt; an existing slide deck to &lt;code&gt;static/&lt;/code&gt; and link using &lt;code&gt;url_slides&lt;/code&gt; parameter in the front matter of the talk file&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Embed&lt;/strong&gt; your slides (e.g. Google Slides) or presentation video on this page using &lt;a href=&#34;https://sourcethemes.com/academic/docs/writing-markdown-latex/&#34;&gt;shortcodes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Further talk details can easily be added to this page using &lt;em&gt;Markdown&lt;/em&gt; and $\rm \LaTeX$ math code.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mapping with Leaflet</title>
      <link>/post/mapping-with-leaflet/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/post/mapping-with-leaflet/</guid>
      <description>
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/htmlwidgets/htmlwidgets.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/pymjs/pym.v1.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;script src=&#34;/rmarkdown-libs/widgetframe-binding/widgetframe.js&#34;&gt;&lt;/script&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This post assumes a basic knowledge of R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using leaflet we can map shapefiles and specific points. As an illustrative example I will be using code I wrote earlier this year when I was
looking into some political economy questions regarding schools and state government.
The shapefiles I will be using are the lower and upper legislatures for the state of
Wisconsin. The points I will be mapping in the second post of this series will be specific
school locations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The goal of this post is to explain how to make an interactive map as below.
This map allows user interaction: zooming in and out, clicking on areas
to show details of that area, removing or adding of layers (top right corner).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34; style=&#34;width:100%;height:480px;&#34; class=&#34;widgetframe html-widget&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/json&#34; data-for=&#34;htmlwidget-1&#34;&gt;{&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;url&#34;:&#34;/post/2020-05-01-mapping-with-leaflet_files/figure-html//widgets/widget_unnamed-chunk-3.html&#34;,&#34;options&#34;:{&#34;xdomain&#34;:&#34;*&#34;,&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;:false,&#34;lazyload&#34;:false}},&#34;evals&#34;:[],&#34;jsHooks&#34;:[]}&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The main libraries we will be using are &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/tigris/tigris.pdf&#34;&gt;tigris&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href=&#34;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/leaflet/leaflet.pdf&#34;&gt;leaflet&lt;/a&gt;.
Let’s start by loading these packages and then downloading the lower and upper legislative
district shapefiles via tigris.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;library(tigris)                                                          # 1
library(leaflet)                                                         # 2
WiscoCdUpper&amp;lt;-state_legislative_districts(state=&amp;quot;WI&amp;quot;, house = &amp;quot;upper&amp;quot;,   # 3
  year=2013, cb=TRUE)                                                    # 4
WiscoCdLower&amp;lt;-state_legislative_districts(state=&amp;quot;WI&amp;quot;, house = &amp;quot;lower&amp;quot;,   # 5
  year=2013, cb=TRUE)                                                    # 6
centerLNG&amp;lt;--90                                                           # 7
centerLAT&amp;lt;-44.8                                                          # 8&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The arguments arguments are fairly self explanatory:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;state&lt;/strong&gt;: the state that you want to retrieve shapefiles for. Accepts State FIPS or state abbreviation.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;house&lt;/strong&gt;: indicates which legislative districts you want. Takes lower or upper as an argument&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;year&lt;/strong&gt;: the districts that were active in this year&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;cb&lt;/strong&gt;: an argument for adjusting level of detail. FALSE is default and is the high detail map. TRUE returns a less detailed map.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The variables centerLNG and centerLAT are longitude and latitude coordinate that I will be using to center my map around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The interactive mapping package I use is leaflet, it will allow us to layer different shapefiles
over a base map.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first want to store this information that will be popping up to a vector to feed into leaflet’s
command. Now within our spatial polygon data frame, we can access the ID of each shape. these
take the form of SSDDD where SS is a two digit state FIPS code, and DDD is a 3 digit district
number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r numCode R numberLines&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;districtinfo &amp;lt;- paste0(&amp;quot;Lower District: &amp;quot;, substr(WiscoCdLower$GEOID, 3, 5))  # 1
mapcolors&amp;lt;-rainbow(length(WiscoCdLower@data$GEOID))                           # 2
rnum&amp;lt;-sample(nrow(WiscoCdLower@data))                                         # 3
pal &amp;lt;- colorFactor(mapcolors[rnum], WiscoCdLower@data$GEOID)                  # 4
lowermap&amp;lt;-leaflet(options = leafletOptions(minZoom = 4)) %&amp;gt;%                  # 5
  addProviderTiles(&amp;quot;CartoDB.Positron&amp;quot;, group = &amp;quot;base&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%                    # 6
  setView(centerLNG, centerLAT, zoom = 6) %&amp;gt;%                                 # 7
  setMaxBounds(-94, 41, -85, 48) %&amp;gt;%                                          # 8
  addPolygons(data = WiscoCdLower, color = &amp;quot;white&amp;quot;, weight = 2,               # 9
    fillColor = ~pal(GEOID), fillOpacity = 0.5, popup = districtinfo,        # 10
    group = &amp;quot;Lower&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%                                                     # 11
  addLayersControl(baseGroups = c(&amp;quot;base&amp;quot;), overlayGroups = c(&amp;quot;Lower&amp;quot;))       # 12&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Going line by line:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol style=&#34;list-style-type: decimal&#34;&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define the text that we want to appear in the information when users click an area of the map&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Define a vector of colors with length equal to the number of districts&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Since our code in line 2 would have similar colors next to each other, I want to shuffle the colors
to make it look better (more info &lt;a href=&#34;https://campus.datacamp.com/courses/machine-learning-with-caret-in-r/regression-models-fitting-them-and-evaluating-their-performance?ex=6&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a dataframe with color information and an id for each district.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Leaflet conveniently allows for piping. To start the map generation, lets limit users to only be able to zoom out so far.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This provides a base map where we will lay our other shapes on top of. We can label this so we can refer to
it later (in line 12).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;This sets the initial view, centered on a latitude and longitude point with a certain initial zoom&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To restrict the user from venturing too far from your area of interest you can restrict the frame of the map.
To see this, try to pull the map in any direction, you can’t get too far until it bounces you back to a relevant frame.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Here is where we layer our district shapefile on top of that base map we established in line 6.
Leaflet recognizes the Spatial Polygon Dataframe as such and knows how to handle it. The color option sets the
color of the border of the districts and the weight is how thick these borders are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Continuing with the district shapefile options. To fill the shapes with different colors,
we use the colors we generated in lines 2-4. The fillOpacity command allows you to adjust
how much you can see through the shape. Notice how you can still make out information on
the base map? That’s because we set this option to less than 1. The popup option is telling
leaflet we want to see districtinfo for the area we are clicking on in the map.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We can label this layer as “Lower”, this allows us to refer to it in the layers control below.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lastly, this layer control allows us to tell leaflet that we want the “base” to always be
visible on the map, but we can add/remove “Lower”. To see this in the map below click the icon
in the upper right corner. Notice how we can uncheck and recheck “Lower”? But we can’t do that
with the base map.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div id=&#34;htmlwidget-2&#34; style=&#34;width:100%;height:480px;&#34; class=&#34;widgetframe html-widget&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/json&#34; data-for=&#34;htmlwidget-2&#34;&gt;{&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;url&#34;:&#34;/post/2020-05-01-mapping-with-leaflet_files/figure-html//widgets/widget_unnamed-chunk-6.html&#34;,&#34;options&#34;:{&#34;xdomain&#34;:&#34;*&#34;,&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;:false,&#34;lazyload&#34;:false}},&#34;evals&#34;:[],&#34;jsHooks&#34;:[]}&lt;/script&gt;
We can then add an additional layer to this map with the upper house as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;districtinfo &amp;lt;- paste0(&amp;quot;Lower District: &amp;quot;, substr(WiscoCdLower$GEOID,3,5),  # 1
  &amp;quot; &amp;lt;br&amp;gt; &amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Upper District: &amp;quot;, substr(WiscoCdUpper$GEOID,3,5))             # 2
loweranduppermap&amp;lt;-leaflet(options = leafletOptions(minZoom = 4)) %&amp;gt;%        # 3
  addProviderTiles(&amp;quot;CartoDB.Positron&amp;quot;, group = &amp;quot;base&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%                  # 4
  setView(centerLNG, centerLAT, zoom = 6) %&amp;gt;%                               # 5
  setMaxBounds(-94, 41, -85, 48) %&amp;gt;%                                        # 6
  addPolygons(data = WiscoCdLower, color = &amp;quot;white&amp;quot;, weight = 2,             # 7
    fillColor = ~pal(GEOID), fillOpacity = 0.5,                             # 8
    popup = districtinfo, group = &amp;quot;Lower&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%                              # 9
  addPolygons(data = WiscoCdUpper, weight =2, opacity = 1,                 # 10
    color = &amp;quot;black&amp;quot;, fill = FALSE, group = &amp;quot;Upper&amp;quot;) %&amp;gt;%                    # 11
  addLayersControl(baseGroups = c(&amp;quot;base&amp;quot;),                                 # 12
    overlayGroups = c(&amp;quot;Upper&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;Lower&amp;quot;))                                   # 13&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are only a few changes we needed to make. In line 1 and 2 we define our pop up
to show information on both the lower and upper legislative districts. In lines 10 and 11
we add in the upper house as an additional layer. Setting fill to false we can just have the
boundary of the upper legislative districts, this will allow us to see through to the lower
legislative district layer. And lastly in line 12 and 13 we add our upper legislative districts
into the map. Notice if you open the layer control in the map below (upper right corner), you
can now check/uncheck both the lower and the upper legislative districts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;htmlwidget-3&#34; style=&#34;width:100%;height:480px;&#34; class=&#34;widgetframe html-widget&#34;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;script type=&#34;application/json&#34; data-for=&#34;htmlwidget-3&#34;&gt;{&#34;x&#34;:{&#34;url&#34;:&#34;/post/2020-05-01-mapping-with-leaflet_files/figure-html//widgets/widget_unnamed-chunk-8.html&#34;,&#34;options&#34;:{&#34;xdomain&#34;:&#34;*&#34;,&#34;allowfullscreen&#34;:false,&#34;lazyload&#34;:false}},&#34;evals&#34;:[],&#34;jsHooks&#34;:[]}&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time Flexibility, Women’s Wages, and the Gender Wage Gap</title>
      <link>/publication/journal-article/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/publication/journal-article/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
