<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Syllabus | Joseph M. Westenberg</title>
    <link>/courses/example/</link>
      <atom:link href="/courses/example/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Syllabus</description>
    <generator>Source Themes Academic (https://sourcethemes.com/academic/)</generator><language>en-us</language><copyright>© Joseph Westenberg 2021</copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>/images/logo_huc1be9e4e3ae24305730dfe0ccc5f8623_97775_300x300_fit_lanczos_2.png</url>
      <title>Syllabus</title>
      <link>/courses/example/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Page 1</title>
      <link>/courses/example/lesson0/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/courses/example/lesson0/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;getting-started-in-r&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting Started in R&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I assume you have R installed and running. There are plenty of guides online on how to do this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s first define some arrays within R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These can be numeric based, in this case integer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r numCode R numberLines&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;A&amp;lt;-c(5,6,7)  # 1
B&amp;lt;-c(7,8,9)  # 2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s dig into what is going on a bit more. We are telling R to define a vector, this is the c( ) part, with elements 1,2,3 and give that vector a name A. The backwards arrow tells R what is the name and what is the element we are defining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can make character based vectors as well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r numCode R numberLines&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;C&amp;lt;-c(&amp;quot;a&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;b&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;c&amp;quot;)  # 1
D&amp;lt;-c(&amp;quot;d&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;e&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;f&amp;quot;)  # 2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can then combine these vectors into a dataframe (this is relevant for when we start thinking about reading in/manipulating actual data). Since all of our vectors are length three, we can easily create a dataframe (think a matrix) where our column names will be the name of the vectors, and the rows will be the elements of the vectors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r numCode R numberLines&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;first_dataframe&amp;lt;-data.frame(A,B,C,D)  # 1
print(first_dataframe)                # 2&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##   A B C D
## 1 5 7 a d
## 2 6 8 b e
## 3 7 9 c f&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now first_dataframe is going to be of similar format as we will typically have when we read in data from excel files into R.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class=&#34;r numCode R numberLines&#34;&gt;&lt;code&gt;print(first_dataframe[1,])  # 1&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;##   A B C D
## 1 5 7 a d&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Page 2</title>
      <link>/courses/example/lesson1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>/courses/example/lesson1/</guid>
      <description>


&lt;div id=&#34;project-organization&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Project Organization&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we get started, let’s set up a folder for our project and create subfolders to keep things organized. For this project I recommend the following subfolders, which are a good minimum for organizing any project:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;raw_data: This is where we will put our `preprocessed’ data we will be getting from MIT Election Lab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;scripts: Where we will save all of our R-scripts in this folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;processed_data: If we want to save some intermediate data steps between raw data and our output.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tables: Any tex tables we generate we will save to this folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;figures: Any figures we generate we will save to this folder&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;tex: Where we can have our paper and/or presentations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can make more folders if you feel it keeps you organized. The main point I want to make here is it is well worth your time to think about how you want to organize your project. Oftentimes if we jump right in without a plan, things become a jumbled mess. (If you want to go further with your organization strategies, I recommend looking into waf, specifically check out &lt;a href=&#34;https://econ-project-templates.readthedocs.io/en/stable/index.html&#34;&gt;Templates for Reproducible Research Projects in Economics&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My project folder now looks like this:
&lt;strong&gt;Insert image of folder&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;getting-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Getting Data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s start by downloading &lt;a href=&#34;https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataset.xhtml?persistentId=doi:10.7910/DVN/PEJ5QU#&#34;&gt;Senate data from MIT Election Lab’s website&lt;/a&gt;. Let’s choose the csv format and save it in your raw_data folder. Next let’s download &lt;a href=&#34;https://dataverse.harvard.edu/dataset.xhtml?persistentId=doi:10.7910/DVN/IG0UN2&#34;&gt;House of Representatives data from MIT Election Lab&lt;/a&gt; again in csv format.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id=&#34;reading-in-the-data&#34; class=&#34;section level2&#34;&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Reading in the data&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s open up a blank R script.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
